Unknown: No. See ya.
When people
gradually started to
learn that I was
researching Jewish
music, a lot of
people said oh, you
must speak to Rudy
lever.
No. When I first met
Rudy, which was at
the Bradford
synagogue, I asked
him what his story
was, as it were, he
talked about his
youth, and then the
Nazi occupation,
etc. And how he come
to England. And he
talked a little bit
about how he'd been
a singer in the
synagogue, most of
his life, eventually
became the Kanto the
Brentwood synagogue.
He played violin, as
a child, but had
never had any kind
of formal
theoretical,
university level
type of education in
music. In fact, he
was a dentist, very
good dentist, I
believe. But he's
kept that music
going. And then in
the nine in the 70s,
he composed Enosh
not I don't know if
it was exactly out
of the blue, but it
seems to be out of
the blue
he told me about
this in a very
matter of fact, way.
Oh, yeah. And then
in the 70s I, I
composed this opera,
as he called it. Not
quite accurate, but
that doesn't matter.
I composed his opera
called Enosh. What's
that today it's a
it's a thing for
chorus and full
orchestra solos.
Background
training. Content
Rudy was very
musically
knowledgeable, from
a sort of very
advanced amateur
level. He knew his
opera very well. He
was an admirer of
Bach, and Mozart,
Beethoven, all
sorts of class
either played the
piano, Chopin,
Schubert, Beethoven,
and my mother sang
as a
child or his father
had some LPs, I
think, that they
listened to, I think
one of them was the
Berlioz enfants
DocList, which
remained a very dear
piece to him
throughout his life
and was performed in
the same concept as
well an extract from
it was was performed
in same concert as
Enosh. And so he had
he was steeped in a
sort of Western
classical music
tradition, as well
as a synagogue music
tradition, some of
which is very
similar to that
western classical
tradition, but some
of it some of which
is not. And it's
very almost Islamic
in nature, or
Arabic, certainly,
in its influences.
And so what I think
he was trying to
achieve was to to
meld the meld his
his knowledge of
classical music with
that synagogue
tradition.
Now see ya
it's like an
oratoria
Really it's it's can
you? Kid.
Rudy, didn't just
leave the tunes as
they were. He sort
of intervened
musically, he
changed aspects of
some of the what we
might call hymns,
synagogue. The
classic one is Enosh
mankind, which is
sung on Yom Kippur
war. It's very
serious. It's sort
of the end of a long
process of praying
and singing towards
the end of a fast.
It's very well known
in the Jewish world.
But he changed
aspects of harmony
sort of played
around with the
rhythm a little bit.
You'll hear it start
and you'll think,
Oh, yes, that's in
our show. And then
you'll hear
something a bit
different. And
you'll think, Oh,
that's not quite
what I remember. And
it makes you think
more about the music
rather than just
hearing a familiar
tune. What he was
trying to do is to
is to sort of feed
into a tradition, or
two traditions, the
duration, that
Western classical
music, but to
disrupt it a little
bit and draw our
attention to certain
things. And the
soloists music is in
a much more modern
idiom. It's
beautifully written
actually.
Men and women they,
the story is of the
Jewish people,
essentially, it
starts with the
people of Israel,
being happy to have
arrived in the
Promised Land. And
then it becomes
gradually more
serious as they're
overtaken by various
events throughout
history. Whilst it's
never upfront,
explicitly
expressed, you can
identify particular
historical things,
and eventually
coming to the
Holocaust. And
there's a moment
where there's
obvious references
to Hitler without
naming him and to
the horrors that
were perpetrated
upon the Jewish
people. And then
after that, there is
a short epilogue, I
guess, whereby there
is a sort of sign of
hope for the future,
I would say a
qualified hope, not
A, not an a sort of
an ecstatic,
uncontrolled hope.
But there is a sort
of root space for
reflection and
optimism.
It's off my mouth,
and the meditation
is acceptable.
He left Germany
quite early on in
his childhood, and
he left before the
worst of the
atrocities
otherwise, one might
assume, sadly, that
he wouldn't have
survived. So thank
God, he did leave.
So he never spoke to
me about that
individually, but I
knew the the
history, more or
less.
We went by train,
ship, train, and
then train. I liked
travelling, the
excitement,
I think, whilst
again, he never
articulated it
precisely. I think
that that was quite
a powerful personal,
I wouldn't say
reconciliation with
but engagement with
an expression of
that trauma that
survivors suffer. I
think certainly the
the power of the
music that he wrote,
that comes from
somewhere. I think
he was working
through a number of
historical emotional
aspects
from Hamburg to brim
a half and we had
the compartment to
ourselves. Then the
customs officer came
around, he asked my
father to go to
another compartment.
We stopped at a
station. When we set
off I said, Where's
daddy? My mother was
just as frightened.
But she said, he'll
be along. They had
asked him questions
and body searched
him. He
did talk about his,
his escape, for want
of a better word,
the music and the
narrative in the
text works through
some of that idea of
escape, and finding
a better life
somewhere. And then,
the risk of it all
happening again, and
eventual partial
catharsis. So
there was a tender
to take us on the
ship to the key
side. We went to the
station. It seemed
very dark. It was
November. So it got
dark early. It was
raining, there were
gas lights, and the
train puffed a lot
of steam. That was
our entry to
England. And the new
and better life.
One could tell when
he felt something
very deeply. He's
very sincere man.
Very gentle man. I
would say. My, one
of my main impulses
behind doing it was
yes, there's a self
interest in terms of
the research and the
the potential
academic outcomes
and things like
that. But actually,
the most important
thing for me was to
do it to get it done
for Rudy. Because he
kept saying to me,
I'm on a limited
timescale here. He
knew that he
wouldn't be
surviving another 20
years or something
and that it needed
to be done there.
And then and so,
within the kind of
confines of what I
could do, I wanted
to do it for him
primarily